<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Old English loyalty &amp; policy agreeable to primitive Christianity. The first part by the author of The beginning and progress of a needfull and hopefull reformation.</title>
            <author>Stephens, Edward, d. 1706.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 97 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61435</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5433</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32555</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12724901</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12724901</idno>
            <idno type="VID">66322</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61435)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 66322)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1027:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Old English loyalty &amp; policy agreeable to primitive Christianity. The first part by the author of The beginning and progress of a needfull and hopefull reformation.</title>
                  <author>Stephens, Edward, d. 1706.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 44 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed in the year 1691, published 1695,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1695]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages stained with print showthrough and loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Government.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  England.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:66322:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:66322:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Old Engliſh</hi> Loyalty &amp; Policy Agreeable to <hi>PRIMITIVE CHRISTIANITY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Firſt PART.</p>
            <p>By the Author of <hi>The Beginning and Progreſs of a Needfull and Hopefull Reformation.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Jer. xlviij. 10.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Curſed be he that doth the Work of the Lord deceitfully, or <hi>negligently.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Peſtis Patriae Pigrities.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed in the Year 1691. Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed 1695.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:66322:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:66322:2"/>
            <head>To Their Excellent Majeſties King <hi>WILLIAM</hi> &amp; Queen <hi>MARY.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe Your Majeſties,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Preſume I may ſay without Vanity, that as no Man hath more heartily deſir'd, ſo none hath more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly and unmoveably endeavour'd, in the way which I take to be moſt direct and certain, to promote the Honour and Proſperity of Your Majeſties, than my ſelf. And though to the generality of the Men of this degenerate Age I may ſeem to have treated you with leſs Reſpect than I ought; yet to Your own Royal Judgments, enlarged with a Noble ſenſe of Piety, Virtue and Generoſity, I cannot doubt but the following Pages will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate the contrary: and that I have treated you with greater Honour, than their narrow Sentiments could imagine. It is true, I had a principal Reſpect to the Honor of that Tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Majeſty, to which all Creatures ought always to be ready to ſacrifice their little Sparks of Honour, and their Lives and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. And to make the poor degenerate Mortals of this Age in ſome ſort ſenſible of their Stupidity and great Inſenſibility of the Honour due to that Glorious Majeſty, I know not any thing that could have a more direct Tendency and Efficacy, than with great Fidelity to intermix ſuch Freedom as might excite ſome ſenſe and concern for the Honour due to a much inferiour Majeſty, of a Mortal. And from this Principle may be deduc'd an unanſwerable Conviction of a double Fault in moſt of thoſe who ſhall cenſure me for it: <hi>1.</hi> Of want of due and proportionable Concern for the Honour of that Supreme Majeſty upon juſt and great occaſion. <hi>2.</hi> Of want of due Concern at the Diſhonour done to Your Majeſties, not in Words, but in treacherous and unworthy Actions. He
<pb facs="tcp:66322:3"/>who can acquit himſelf of the due diſcharge of his Duty in theſe reſpects, may be allow'd to caſt the firſt Stone of Cenſure at me.</p>
            <p>Your Majeſties have done your ſelves no little Honour in reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what I have done, not as ſome mean Souls expected, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps deſired; but ſo as hath confirmed the Honourable Opinion, which I and many others had of your Virtues. And as I much rejoyce to ſee it, ſo it is matter of great pity and grief to me to ſee ſo much Virtue and ſo noble <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertakings ſo encumber'd and peſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er'd with ſo much Sordidneſs, Baſeneſs and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfaithfulneſs, as I cannot but obſerve in ſome, who ſhould be, were they like their Anceſtors, the Honour and Glory of the Nation. But I hope Your Virtues, by the Favour and Bleſſing of Almighty God, will ſpedily ſubdue all that Wickedneſs and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfaithfulneſs to God and to Your ſelves, which you muſt firſt encounter with at home, and then all Your Enemies abroad, and at laſt obtain an Eternal Victory. Which is the hearty Deſire and daily Prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Majeſties Humble and moſt faithfull Subject.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:66322:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Old Engliſh</hi> Loyalty &amp; Policy Agreeable to <hi>PRIMITIVE CHRISTIANITY.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE great <hi>Oppoſition</hi> which hath always been made by the <hi>Kingdom of Darkneſs</hi> againſt the <hi>Kingdom of Light,</hi> and by the <hi>Seed of the Serpent</hi> againſt the <hi>Seed of the Woman,</hi> may eaſily be perceived by any who carefully read the Sacred Scriptures, or will conſider the Actions of Men upon Earth, form the beginning. In this oppoſition there is nothing more admirable and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazing, than to ſee ſuch as may charitably be believed to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the Kingdom of Light, notwithſtanding in many things ſo greatly abuſed as to become ſubſervient to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of the Kingdom of Darkneſs. Yet that ſo it often is, may be plainly obſerved: and as plainly, that it always proceeds from ſome relicks of <hi>Carnal Affections,</hi> or of <hi>Impreſſions of the World</hi> too eaſily admitted, in which the <hi>Powers of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> preſide, and often prevail under ſome <hi>Appearance</hi> or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; moſt commonly of Zeal for the Truth, or for the Church; of Prudence, of Proviſion for Families, and the like. And few there are who can ſay, <hi>The Prince of this World cometh, and hath nothing in me;</hi> Jo. 14.30. few to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:66322:4"/>whom it may not be ſaid, <hi>How can ye believe, who receive Honour one of another, and ſeek not the Honour that cometh from God only?</hi> (Jo. 5.44.) few that regard thoſe impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Admonitions. How hard is it for a <hi>Rich Man</hi> to enter into the Kingdom of Heaven, or the genuine ſtate of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity: and few who take half ſo much pains to purifie their Souls by Mortification of Carnal and Worldly Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as they do to feed and gratifie thoſe Affections.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Heroick Vertues of the antient Chriſtians</hi> we reject as Popery, and leave to the Cells, or neglect as peculiar to times of Perſecution. Which we may again pull down upon our ſelves, if we make it more neceſſary for us, than our ſelves fit for enjoyment of ſuch a deliverance as we for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally profeſs to acknowledge. Theſe Affections we indulge not only in our liberal uſe of Neceſſaries, but even in Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluities; in the Pomps and Vanities of the World, and in inſatiable purſuit thereof, even often by indirect means, though moſt ſolemnly renounced at our Baptiſm; and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt the Senſe, and the moſt expreſs Doctrine of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Scripture, that we may do it with the more freedom. Nor are theſe the faults of the groſly vicious and profane only, but ſuch as it is rare to find any of the beſt ſo free from, but the Prince of this World may find ſomething to take hold on, and make them too often ſubſervient to his Intereſt.</p>
            <p>Though <hi>Pride</hi> was the occaſion of the Fall of Angels, and is the very Diaboliſm (if I may ſo ſay) of the Devils, who being in truth dependent Beings, would ſet up for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent Deities, and be worſhipped and adored and ſerved by their fellow Creatures (which was ſo well underſtood and conſidered by the ancient Chriſtians, that they reputed <hi>Humility</hi> one of the firſt, moſt neceſſary fundamental Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, and declined all worldly Honour, and Applauſe of Men as carefully and circumſpectly as we ſee it now ſtudiouſly and earneſtly purſued,) yet is there nothing more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon among us than to ſee People, otherwiſe ſober, of good
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:66322:4"/>parts, and ſincerely religious, yet ſo infatuated with Vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glory, Oſtentation, Formality and Affectation or Conceited<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as even to render themſelves ridiculous and pitied by thoſe of whom they ſeek Applauſe, or to be admired; and ſo miſerably enchanted and inſlaved by this Devil, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their own Experience, nor the Admonition of faithful Friends can reclaim them: But they carry their own Rod at their Backs, and that as certain and ſmart as one would wiſh. In others, who have eſcaped the groſneſs of this Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, yet is it often manifeſt by their Concern for the Honor of very Trifles; as ſome Criticiſm, or new Diſcovery or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, or other Atchievment; and many times, when in truth it is not due to them, but perhaps to ſome other more worthy Perſon, who did little regard it. This alſo I have ſometimes had occaſion to pity, and to wiſh that ſuch dead Flies did not ſpoil a good Ointment. There are others who have neither much of the Vanity of the firſt, nor the Induſtry to give them any occaſion for the laſt, in whom notwithſtanding the ſame root may be diſcovered, if they be but touched with ſome punctilio of Honor, or where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they ſuppoſe their Reputation concerned; or but affron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with ſome honeſt, plain, friendly and free Admonition or Advice. This will certainly draw out the very ſame Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, which only lay a little deeper concealed; for it ſhall be reſented to the loſs not only of the Eſteem of others, but of the good Offices of the moſt faithful and cordial Friends, which they willfully deprive themſelves of, by a greater Folly than the former. Theſe are not onely ſuch dead Flies as corrupt the Savour of their Civil Converſation; but ſuch living Flies as corrupt the very Eſſence of their beſt Actions, and diminiſh their Treaſure of Eternal Reward; and beſides, expoſe ſuch as are not very watchfull againſt them to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſubſervient in divers reſpects to the Deſigns of that Kingdom of Darkneſs. While they have ſo lively a Senſe of Honor either paid or neglected; in reſpect of themſelves, or of other mortal men, which may be their own eaſe, the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:66322:5"/>impreſſions of that are apt to divert the mind from the due apprehenſions and regard of the far greater Honor to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to God, when both do concur in the ſame caſe, and the circumſtances of the latter are not ſo plain and obvious as thoſe of the former. And whereas in ſome ſuch caſes there may be juſt cauſe a little to neglect the former, out of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the latter: yet cannot that be done without ſome Cenſure and Indignation proceeding from a ſecret byaſs in ſuch Minds (though otherwiſe well affected to Religion) which may eaſily be heighthned to a direct Oppoſition of ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good Works under an appearance of Prudence, Diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Duty. And nothing is more common than for men in ſuch caſes to quarrel at the Manner, when they have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to ſay againſt the Matter. This is a ſubject which well deſerves to be more largely treated, but this is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to be here briefly noted for my preſent occaſion. And therefore I will onely admoniſh ſuch perſons to reflect upon themſelves whenever they are concerned for the Honor of Men, and conſider well, whether their concern for the Honour of God be proportionable.</p>
            <p>Nor is it onely from the Heroick Vertue of the Ancient Chriſtians that we are ſo degenerated, but even from <hi>the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Genius of the Engliſh Nation.</hi> The one we have reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted as Popery and Superſtition; and the other as Moroſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Ruſticity: And while we affected a more refined Courtſhip of the <hi>French,</hi> had almoſt in effect courted our ſelves into a <hi>French</hi> Slavery. Nay, ſo baſe and inconſiderate hath been the Flattery of ſome men for their own Advantage, that it hath not onely corrupted our Court, and endanger'd our Civil Conſtitution, but even profaned our Churches and Sacred Offices, and brought great difficulties upon our Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, but greateſt of all upon our Princes. It is true, it hath been the Unhappineſs of the Princes themſelves to be ſo ill ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed as to give encouragement to ſuch People, who are always moſt forward to obtrude themſelves, and ſo to raiſe up ſuch an Evil Genius: But raiſed it hath been, and hath ſo far
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:66322:5"/>prevailed, that any thing of the honeſt, plain, downright old Engliſh Genius and Loyalty, which prefers the Honor and Safety of the King and Kingdom before Favour and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferments, or any private Reſpects, cannot but appear like an uncouth thing, and little leſs than Madneſs to our refined Frenchified Courtiers. But, <hi>Naturam expellas furca licet uſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que recurrit:</hi> And though the true Engliſh Genius hath withdrawn it ſelf a while, it will appear again with ſo much the greater vigor in due time. And that time, I doubt not, is now come, or near at hand. For God himſelf, who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways favours Sincerity and downright Honeſty, though he many times permits Evil men to expoſe themſelves and the Wickedneſs of their own Genius, that others beholding the ſame may ſo much the more abhor it, hath now raiſed us up a King according to our own temper; and though he hath hitherto permitted him to feel the Evil Conſequences of ſuch mens Prudentials, will I hope henceforward make him ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible thereof, and direct him to and by better Counſels.</p>
            <p>But at preſent whoever ſhall be ſo hardy as to offer him his Service in ſuch a caſe as this, in honeſt and plain terms, muſt expect no mean Oppoſition, Cenſures from all, and Calumnies, if no worſe, from theſe laſt preſcribed. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſince I am Debtor not onely to the Wiſe, but to the Unwiſe alſo, whoſe Good and Reformation, not hurt in the leaſt, I heartily deſire, I think fit for their better Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and to prevent miſtake, and remove their unjuſt Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, to give ſome farther <hi>Account of my ſelf and my Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours hitherto</hi> in this matter. And then I ſhall add with the ſame Integrity and Plainneſs what I think farther neceſſary to be ſaid for the Service of the King and my Country; and with the ſame Freedom I would uſe if I was now to bid farewell to the World.</p>
            <p>I have lived now near threeſcore years in the World, and, before this King came to the Crown, have ſeen, beſides the troubleſome part of a former Reign, and twelve years <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regnum,</hi> two Reigns full of great Miſcarriages, of horrid Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>impiety
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:66322:6"/>againſt God, and the higheſt Violations of Juſtice to Man, tending to the Deſtruction of a Noble Conſtitution, and the Enſlaving of my Country: And I have been from my Youth a great Lover of my Country, and an indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious Student of the Good of Mankind, even to the neglect and detriment of my private Concerns: yet did I never attempt any ſuch Service to either of thoſe Kings, as ſince the late happy Revolution, I have done to this. And this may ſerve to ſatisfie ſuch as know me not, that it is not any Humour, but ſome ſpecial Cauſe and Conſideration, which hath moved me to what I have done of late. Again, I ſoon had a great Family, and but a ſmall Eſtate, and have met with great Diſappointments by perſons I have dealt with; yet did I never count any Preferment, though I have been much in Town, and have had ſuch friends as wanted nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good Will nor Opportunity to have given me Aſſiſtance. But I have always abſtained even from thoſe common Courtſhips, which are in uſe with many in my circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and thir principal Means to get into buſineſs: I have abſtained not onely from Diſhoneſt, but ſuch common ways of Gain, as I thought ſordid and more unworthy than mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner Employments or a Mean Condition. And I often remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, <hi>The Earth is the Lord's, and the Fulneſs thereof;</hi> deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to approve my ſelf to Him, and leave my Portion of thoſe things to his Aſſignment. By theſe means my Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath been fair, though my Eſtate but ſmall, and I have lived in good Eſteem with the beſt people, and perſons of good quality. And this may ferve to ſatisfie the ſame per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, that, it is not any private Concern that hath been my Motive in theſe things.</p>
            <p>But the plain truth in both theſe Caſes is this: That I did not expreſs my Fidelity to the two laſt Princes in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, it was becauſe I ſaw them not capable of it: And when I have ſometimes had it in my thoughts, I have ſound as great ſecret Reſtraints upon my Mind, as I have ſince, in what I have done, found Freedom and Excitation. That I have ſince
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:66322:6"/>expreſſed my ſelf in this manner to their preſent Majeſties, it was, next to the Service of the Supreme Majeſty, firſt, my great Concern for them, and for their Proſperity, and for the Succeſs of a moſt noble Cauſe not a little concerned therein: and next, an honourable Opinion of their Vertue, that they had both Wiſdom to diſcern, at leaſt, the Hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty and integrity of my Intentions; and Piety to take well ſo well-meant Admonitions in a caſe of ſo great Importance, without Indignation for a little plain bluntneſs in the manner of it. And I was well ſatisfied of the Truth and Importance of it; which appeared ſuch to me, as made me have the leſs regard to any thing elſe.</p>
            <p>I looked upon <hi>the King</hi> as an <hi>Inſtrument</hi> raiſed up by the ſpecial Providence of God for great matters in this Age: But I alſo conſidered that ſuch are uſually lead to ſpecial <hi>Tryals,</hi> wherein, if they be not very circumſpect and reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, they are ſometimes laid aſide, but always involve them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in greater Difficulties. This I underſtood not only by ſtudy, but by my own Experience alſo. And I farther conſidered, how little theſe things are in this Age regarded in Princes Courts, or underſtood even by thoſe whoſe Profeſſion doth oblige them to be better acquainted with them: and what danger might hence ariſe to the King, if he ſhould acquieſce in ſuch miſtaken Counſels. Few Men hath more ſincerely and heartily deſired the Proſperity of their Majeſties: But none, I doubt, have been ſo apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive of his Danger in this reſpect; none ſo early, I verily believe. This made my Heart ake for him, when he had not been long amongſt us, which at laſt broke out in that plain Admonition which I firſt put into his hands at <hi>Hamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton-Court,</hi> not long after his Acceſs to the Throne. This, when Obſervation of the Event had not a little confirmed my former Opinion, provoked my <hi>Reflections upon the firſt years Occurrences:</hi> and upon ſuch farther Obſervation the next year, the <hi>Reflections upon the Engagement at Sea.</hi> And this year again, very much fearing ſome conſiderable Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointment
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:66322:7"/>at leaſt, (if not ſomething worſe, which the Goodneſs and Long-ſuffering of God hath at preſent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained.) I propoſed the Caſe in certain <hi>Queſtions to the Divines of the Church of England,</hi> (which I had before propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſome others, but in writing only) that I might provoke, if poſſible, a due Conſideration of the matter, and of the proper Means to prevent the Miſchiefs I feared. And with this I thought I had done, and did not intend to write more upon this ſubject. Yet was I again engaged in it beyond my intention, in a manner not unworthy to be noted.</p>
            <p>The Matter I had ſo earneſtly contended for was the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation</hi> of the Manners of my Country, exceedingly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved in the late Reigns, and the <hi>Proſperity of his Majeſty,</hi> which I was confident depended very much upon his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Exerciſe of his Royal Authority for that purpoſe. Which had he accordingly performed, and not yielded to pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Counſels, which betrayed him, might have been the Glory of his Reign, and the Foundation of an uninterrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Proſperity and Succeſs. But from this he was unhapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diverted by ſuch as were moſt obliged to have advis'd and perſuaded him better. Nor could any Publick Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, either Civil or Eccleſiaſtical, be prevail'd with to take this Matter, though ſo neceſſary, and of ſo great impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, into conſideration, ſo as to do any thing to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in it. No Man regarding that ſevere Denunciation, <hi>Curſed is he that doth the Work of the Lord negligently;</hi> Jer. 48.10. When all thoſe Powers declined the Service, it pleaſed God that a few private Gentlemen ſhould readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly embrace it; and her Majeſty, upon the firſt Motion, moſt readily heartily and happily, giving Encouragement to it, it preſently had a very hopeful beginning in <hi>Middle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſex</hi> and <hi>London:</hi> and the Example thereof was by the Indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry and Charge of thoſe few private Gentlemen ſoon after recommended to all parts of the Nation, with very good Succeſs in divers places.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:66322:7"/>
            <p>This hopeful beginning the Devil in Man could not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure, but firſt exciting ſome to diſcourage it in private; when he found that would not do, but others ſtepp'd in to help it on, he preſently called a Council againſt it. And when they could find no juſt Matter of Accuſation, in great ſtraits they reſolved to lay hold on the firſt moſt proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ground they could meet with; and though a meer Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumny, dreſs it up as well as they could, and with all their Power and Authority ſtifle this honeſt Undertaking under Colour of Juſtice. And that the Example of this might the more effectually enervate the Power of the other, this muſt be done in the very ſame place, and at the next General-Quarter-Seſſions.</p>
            <p>I had been more concerned for ſuch Matters, than to be unconcerned at, or inſenſible of ſuch an <hi>Effort</hi> of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my againſt this ſo honeſt and hopeful a Beginning; and I was not unacquainted with his Wiles: Beſides, though nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther my Hand nor my Purſe was employed in thoſe worthy and commendable Actions, yet had I perfect Knowledge of all from the beginning: And therefore having been very plain with their Betters, for promoting of ſo good and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary a Cauſe, I could not let ſo Foul, ſo Injuſtice-like, nay ſo Ungentle-man-like an Oppoſition, by ſome unworthy Perſons, who apparently wanted either Law or Integrity to qualifie them for ſuch an Employment, paſs without ſome Animadverſion; which I thought the moſt ſpeedy way, to check the Effects of their Venom, the Poiſon of the Serpent, before it had transfuſed it ſelf over the whole Body of the Nation.</p>
            <p>This was no ſooner printed, and comunicated to ſome Friends in private before Publication, but I ſoon perceived <hi>another Effort,</hi> to ſtifle it in the Birth; not by the Violence or Projects of real Enemies, but by means of the Errors and Miſtakes of deceived, well-meaning Friends. <hi>Her Majeſty</hi>'s <hi>Letter</hi> had ſo great a ſhare in theſe things, that it could not be paſſed by in Silence, without Ingratitude to her Piety,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:66322:8"/>and Injury to the Relation. Nor could it be mentioned without taking notice of that <hi>ſpecial Favour of God,</hi> which ſo cloſely and remarkably attend it, unleſs I ſhould have neglected the moſt ſacred and neceſſary part of Hiſtory: Nor could that be noted without as remarkable an Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon <hi>Succeſs of His Majeſty's Affairs</hi> now again this third Summer; but I muſt have committed the ſame Fault in this Particular alſo, and been unfaithful to the great and important Cauſe in which I was engaged. And the concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of theſe two Obſervables this Year, and their Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with what I had again and again obſerved before, and the Importance thereof to His Majeſty for the future, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked me to repreſent thoſe few neceſſary things unto him with that Freedom and Plainneſs, which divers Circumſtances required, and was moſt like to excite his moſt ſerious Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of them. Which was as great an Act of Fidelity and Good Will to him, I think, as a mortal Man could well expreſs. And yet for theſe and theſe only, which come ſo cloſe to the point of the great buſineſs of all, have I been encountred with no ſmall oppſition to the Publication by very good Friends, and Perſons otherwiſe very well affected to the Work in hand; not only by friendly Admonitions and gentle Perſuaſions, but little leſs than Denunciation of no ſmall Diſappointment by a Divine Power. Theſe things I took as they were intended, in a friendly manner, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain and again peruſed what I had written; but the more I conſidered, the more was I confirmed and ſatisfied in what I had done: And perceiving the Temptation, and how it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred upon them, and ſo aſſaulted me, without more of doe I ordered the Publication, leaving the Succeſs to him, whoſe Work it is; but thought fit, for the ſatisfaction of ſuch good People, to recommend ſome few things to further Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration.</p>
            <p>And the firſt is, How apt an <hi>Overvaluation</hi> of Ceremonies, and of the Pomp and Vanities of the World, and of Honours and Reſpect to Men (which is one of the <hi>Corruptions of this
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:66322:8"/>Age,</hi> and a great Degeneracy from the Manly Primitive Chriſtianity) is to dazle our Eyes, and make us leſs regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of that <hi>Honour and Reſpect we owe to the Supreme Majeſty of God:</hi> And what <hi>Advantage</hi> the Enemy thereby gain to impoſe upon us to the neglect of ſo great a Duty, for which we ought to be very jealous upon all Occaſions: For thoſe are plainly his Engines, wherewith he aſſaulted even our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour himſelf. And in this Caſe <hi>the Queſtion</hi> was concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Honour of God and the Honour of the King: Whether I ſhould give to God the Honour of his remarka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Providence, and for the King's real Benefit; or neglect that to ſave the Honour of the King, though in ſo doing I ſhould be unfaithful to God, to the King, and to my own Soul? This was plainly the Caſe. And ſuppoſe I have not Certainty on my ſide; yet where there is ſo vaſt a Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, as between the immortal God and a mortal, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides ſinful Man, ſo fair a Probability, I am certain ought to determine the Queſtion.</p>
            <p>The next may be, How apt ſuch an Over-valuation is to dazle the Eyes, and make even good Men leſs regardful of <hi>more ſubſtantial and neceſſary Duties even to Men,</hi> and to give the Enemy the like Advantage to impoſe upon them in ſuch Caſe alſo. For here the Queſtion is between a little point of Honour to be ſaved, but with danger of greater Miſchief, and the Safety of the Perſon and Succeſs of his Affairs, to be ſecured by a reaſonable Humiliation and Self-abaſement, out of a juſt Reſpect to a far greater Majeſty. And here a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain though I have not Certainty; yet the Difference is ſo great, and the Probability ſo great, that I may be certain it ought to determine it on my ſide.</p>
            <p>A third may be this, How <hi>unſafe</hi> it is <hi>for Princes</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie altogether upon ſuch fine Gentlemen, and cautious, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaiſant, reſpectful Courtiers, without ſome of deeper Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, and more faithful Reſolution for their Service a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them. They May ſerve to treat Strangers, but cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly they had need of other kind of Courtiers near their own Perſons, and in their Councils.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:66322:9"/>
            <p>I might here obſerve how great Miſchief this unobſerved and indulged Corruption doth to the Perſons themſelves in whom it prevails, and what Advantages it affords their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my againſt them; how his Engines and Machinations are thereby ſtrength'ned and made more effectual; and ſo ſhew the Reaſons of the ancient Chriſtians Abhorrence of it: But that I ſuppoſe not ſo proper for this place. Yet to ſhew what great Miſchief is thereby done to the Nation, the Good of which is the King's great Buſineſs and proper Duty, I conceive it not beſide my Scope, but well worth the Conſideration of his Majeſty and the Parliament; of which more hereafter in proper place.</p>
            <p>And theſe Conſiderations, without more ſaying, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive may ſatisfie all who have any ſerious Senſe of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God, and of the real Service of his Majeſty, for my inſerting that Obſervation. As for ſuch <hi>Expreſſions</hi> as may be <hi>thought too plain and indecent</hi> to be uſed to a Prince: If a Man perceiving, or ſtrongly apprehending his Prince to be in any great Danger, uſe ſuch Means for his Preſervation, as he thinks neceſſary for that Exigence, though otherwiſe rude and indecent; yet in ſuch Caſe, no wiſe Man would cenſure it as Rudeneſs or Indecency, but approve it as ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Fidelity. But I ſay plainly that he was not only in Danger, but actually damnified already, and in further Danger in the ways wherein he hath been miſled; and a ſofter Voice, at ſuch diſtance as I ſtand, was not like to be ſo taken notice of, as was neceſſary for him to perceive the Miſtake.</p>
            <p>Beſides, if well conſidered, it doth not ſavour of Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence or Indiſcretion, as may ſeem to vulgar Apprehenſions, but of Honour; being a plain Argument of an Honourable Opinion of his Virtue: Of his Generoſity, to take well ſo much Old Engliſh, Plain Dealing, being mix'd with ſo much manifeſt Fidelity and Affection: And of his Prudence and Diſcretion, to apprehend it aright. Whereas to a Perſon of leſs Generoſity and Prudence, it had indeed been great In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcretion
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:66322:9"/>to have uſed it. But this is not all; there is a greater Honour yet done him in this Treatment, by an Honourable Opinion of greater Vertue than all this reſiding in him; and of a more Honourable Eſtate to which he is raiſed, than barely that of a King: That is, of his ſerious Apprehenſion of the Excellence of that Majeſty, whoſe ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Service is the greateſt Honour that any Creature is ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of; and that he hath been raiſed and conducted to ſuch a ſpecial Service. Other Treatment had been below the Excellency of that Majeſty whoſe Cauſe it is, and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with that Fidelity which ought to be performed to ſuch a ſpecial Inſtrument of his, and not well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming a faithful Servant of both. Had I been concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in a Cauſe for my Prince, wherein the greateſt Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the Nation was queſtioned for ſome Offence or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault, I might and ought to have uſed all Freedom and Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs neceſſary to have convinced him of his Fault; nor had I well conſulted the Honour of my Prince if I had done o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe: Much more is this allowable, and a Duty, in the Caſe of the Supreme Majeſty, though a King be concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in it; and doubly ſo, when it is for his Safety and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage. Beſiedes it gives the King a Noble Opportunity, both to exerciſe and to demonſtrate his Virtue, and to give Glory to God, by accepting of a faithful Admonition from the meaneſt of his Subjects, with all due Reſpect to the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Majeſty.</p>
            <p>After all this, if any be yet ſo inchanted with Vanity, as not to be ſatisfied, and yet believe a Deity, that <hi>Reges in ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes Imperium eſt Jovis,</hi> (to ſpeak to Infidels in the Language of Heathens.) For the Conviction of ſuch, I will here on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſay again, in relation to that Paper, what I had before ſaid in the concluſion of another.</p>
            <p>Poſſibly, in the peruſal of that Paper, ſome, who are moſt attentive to the Importance of the Matter, may over-look other things, and think it very good and honeſt: But theſe muſt be Men who have ſome reliſh of ſuch things. But others,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:66322:10"/>who are not much affected with that, will be apt the more to regard the Form, and cenſure it for rude and inſolent; and that I am well pleaſed they ſhould do, and as ſeverely as they will, For I know no better way to convince them of a Fault of their own, than to make them judge themſelves in the Perſon of another. For if I be rude by plain-dealing with my Fellow-Creatures for their Good, who are perhaps, but a little above me in ſome petty, accidental, tranſitory Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, what are they who are not only more rude toward the State, but impious againſt they Creater, or can behold ſuch Rudeneſs and Impiety without any Cenſure, or Endeavour to reſtrain it? Muſt I be cenſured for breaking the Laws of Man, or but of Civility, and out of a good Deſign? And is it equal then that others ſhall be permitted in impudent Contempt of the Religion of the State, and impious violation of the Laws of Almighty God? <hi>Therefore thou art inexcuſable, O Man, whoſoever thou art that judgeſt; for wherein thou judgeſt another, thou condemneſt thy ſelf. And thinkeſt thou, O Man that judgeſt, — and doſt the ſame, that thou ſhalt eſcape the Judgment of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus much for my <hi>Old Engliſh Loyalty,</hi> which none, who underſtand both, can deny to be very agreeable to the <hi>genuine Primitive Chriſtianity.</hi> I come now to my <hi>Old Engliſh Policy.</hi> A brave People they were, who ſeated themſelves here, and they Found a Climate very agreeable to their own <hi>Genius.</hi> Two Aſſaults they have received in their own Territories from their Neighbours of <hi>Normandy</hi> and <hi>France;</hi> the firſt with their Arms, the laſt with their Vices and Treachery: Both prevailed upon degenerate and impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Princes, and by that Means a little ſhog'd the People; but they after the firſt ſoon return'd again to their own Genius; and ſo I doubt not will again now, though the Powers of Vice be more enſlaving than that of Arms. But the Divine Power, which nothing can withſtand, hath ſo far favour'd us, as to raiſe us up a Prince according to our own <hi>Genius.</hi> Only he hath been at firſt expoſed to the Aſſaults of the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:66322:10"/>Powers, reigning in the dregs of the Corruptions of the late Reigns. And though he hath ſuffered much there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, and perhaps loſt thoſe Advantages he can never regain; yet hath he been preſerved, and gain'd, though at a dear rate, that Experience thereby, which if well conſidered and improved, may be of as great Advantage to him another way. Nor will a Divine Power yet be wanting to aſſiſt him, if he be not wanting to it and to himſelf. I was at firſt brought to him by little leſs than a Miracle, when the Week before I could hardly endure a Two Miles Journey in a Coach, or to make a haſty ſtep a-croſs a Chanel; yet the next Week was carried on with that Vigour and Spirit, that I rode eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day conſiderable Journeys for a whole Week toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. I then performed that little Service, in which I was intruſted, with all Fidelity and good Succeſs, only a Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of greater unexpected Succeſs made it needleſs. And I gave a true and impartial Account of all to one near him, which I believe was never truly repreſented to him. And now I am reſolved by the Grace and Aſſiſtance of Almighty God, to perform ſuch a Service, and make things ſo plain, as ſhall have a good Effect, or leave all that ſhall oppoſe or neglect it, inexcuſable even in the ſight of Men, if there be any true Manhood left in the Nation; If there be ſuch a thing as a ſecret Divine Deſignation of Men to certain Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in this Life, as is believed by wiſe and knowing Men; certain I am that there is nothing in my Life, that hath ſo much, or any ſuch Evidence of it as this hath. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhall endeavour to keep back nothing that may be profitable to be obſerved; but declare all that I think neceſſary without regard to any Perſon or Thing, but the Service of God, the King, and my Countrey; for which no good Man can be offended with me: And for the Malice of Evil Men, the Protection of them for whoſe Service I act, is ſufficient for me; and I have Reaſon to expect it.</p>
            <p>The greateſt <hi>Emperor</hi> in the World, in his own Nature, is a poor weak Mortal as other Men are, and ſubject to the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:66322:11"/>like Infirmities. All his Power which he hath more than others, conſiſts in the joint, voluntary Subjection of other Men to him, who are all like himſelf, dependent Beings upon a far more excellent Being, in whoſe Hand is their Breath and Life, and who inſpirits or diſpirits, and turns their Hearts as he pleaſeth. He who believes this indeed will eaſily perceive that his principal Concern and Wiſdom, is to ſecure firſt the Favour of that Supreme Being, and next the Good Will and Affections of all thoſe, who being natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally his Equals, may thereby become ſubject to him, and ſo continue.</p>
            <p>The former cannot be expected, but by an entire Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity and abſolute Subjection of the Will, Deſigns, and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, to the Will of that Supreme Being. If therefore King <hi>William</hi> believes this, and that he is indeed an Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment raiſed up by that Excellent Majeſty for his Special Service, and by his Providence exalted to the Throne for that purpoſe: This he muſt intend and preſer above all things, or elſe he muſt act like a Brute, which follows its ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual or animal Propenſions; or like a Fool or a Madman; not like a rational Creature, upon good Deliberation and Judgment.</p>
            <p>But firſt he muſt endeavour to know, and <hi>be well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with his Maſter, and with his Will,</hi> and to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it by the leaſt Intimation; be preciſely obſervant of it, to follow it fully; and very watchful againſt any the leaſt Tranſgreſſion; knowing aſſuredly that it will certainly turn to Ten times a greater Diſadvantage to him, than the Advantage he expected by it. And he muſt ſtudy <hi>to know himſelf</hi> well; that he is a dependent Creature; hath no Power of himſelf; is ſo eaſily overpowered by other Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that he hath not the Command of his own Faculties or Thoughts for a moment, without the Favour of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter upon whom he depends; and therefore be very careful to walk humbly before him, that his Heart be not at any time lifted up above himſelf, or above his Fellow Creatures,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:66322:11"/>unleſs in the Caſe of his great Maſter; but in his Cauſe he muſt be as cautious not to fail of the greateſt Generoſity and Magnanimity poſſible, without Fear of Men or Devils. And theſe things he muſt endeavour to know, not by a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perficial, ſpeculative Knowledg, but by ſo effectual a Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctical Knowledge as may equal an Experimental, leſt he be ſent to the common Miſtreſs to learn in better, as I have been for a more effectual Knowledge of what I ſtudied and deſired to have acquired at a cheaper rate. But now I know indeed from whence my Strength cometh, and how little I am able to do even at home, if deſtitute of that Aid.</p>
            <p>Theſe things being well known, it is farther to be conſider'd; that the <hi>Service of God,</hi> in relation to the preſent buſineſs, is <hi>two-fold;</hi> the principal the Good of his Creatures; but by accident (it may be) the deſtruction of ſome. And for theſe he hath his <hi>different proper Inſtruments:</hi> For the latter ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily Devils and Wicked Men; but his <hi>Glorious Inſtruments</hi> are principally employed for the Good of Men, their Real Good, whereby they are made better. And this is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Service and Buſineſs of a King. And in this is his Fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, Generoſity, and Virtue, principally to be exerciſed. If it fail or flag in this; it muſt needs degenerate in all the reſt, and make him more like a Butcher, Executioner, or Serjeant, than a Paſtor, Governor or Tutor. And if he neglect this, though he may notwithſtanding be an Inſtrument of ſome Drudgery, yet a Glorious Inſtrument he cannot be. This therefore is the firſt and principal thing to be intended, and moſt vigorouſly proſecuted, and that not only as a <hi>Common Duty</hi> upon all occaſions, but in this Nation, at this time, by K. <hi>William,</hi> upon very conſiderable <hi>ſpecial Occaſions and Obligations.</hi> The great Corruption of the Manners of the Nation, and the Impudence of Impiety are ſuch as make it a ſpecial Obligation, and a ſpecial Provocation to a Generous Mind, to check and ſubdue it. And the extraordinary Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, which hath raiſed him to the Throne, for this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry purpoſe, undoubtedly as much as for any, is another
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:66322:12"/>ſpecial Obligation: And the Providential Admonitions and Corrections of his Neglect hitherto, which he hath ſince met with, a farther. The Judgments denounced in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel againſt Fear, Shame, Negligence, Unprofitableneſs in the Cauſe of Chriſt and Work of the Lord are very ſevere; and theſe being aggravated by ſuch ſpecial Obligations, muſt needs make the Caſe very dangerous indeed. And here by the way it is very fit that all thoſe, who are called to the Office of Watchmen, whether Ordinary or Extraordinary, or upon any ſpecial Occaſion, ſhould be minded of their own Danger in caſe of neglect of their Duty in that reſpect.</p>
            <p>This great and fundamental Service is to be perfomed by earneſt recommending the enacting of ſuch new Laws, as are neceſſary for ſupply of thoſe that are wanting or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective; by commanding and ſtrictly requiring and inforcing the Execution of ſuch as we have already; and by notable Examples of good Diſcipline: Of all which I have ſaid ſo much already, more than once, that I ſhall need to ſay no more here.</p>
            <p>As the Foundation and Stability of Regal Power depends upon the Favour of God, and the Affections of the Subjects, ſo each doth require <hi>continual Demonſtration of Vertue</hi> in them, who are inveſted with it. God who is the Searcher of Hearts, doth not withſtanding require it, and frequently leads them to occaſions of Tryal; and much more may Men, who cannot otherwiſe judge of the Heart, expect it. God doth require it not only in matters of Religion for his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, but alſo in matters of Juſtice to Men, wherein the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of his Supreme Authority alſo is concerned. And Men expect it not only in matters of Juſtice and Benefit to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but alſo in matters of Religion and Honour to God. So that what I have hitherto ſaid concerning the Means of acquiring and ſecuring the Favour of God, hath a farther con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration alſo in reſpect of Men; which even <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> hath taken notice of; whoſe Politicks have more of that Right Reaſon, which Chriſtianity recommends, than moſt of the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:66322:12"/>Politicks of our Modern Statiſts. And that this was a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal part of our old Engliſh Policy, as is very manifeſt in our old Laws and Hiſtorians.</p>
            <p>But to come to our <hi>Civil Politicks,</hi> It hath been obſerved by Wiſe Men, that there is a certain <hi>Natural Diſpoſition</hi> in moſt Nations, and in many very apparent, to ſome certain Form of Government peculior to their own <hi>Genius,</hi> by which they are more eaſily to be governed than by any other. And if the Governors act ſutable to that diſpoſition of the People, it uſually makes all very happy. We have now a <hi>Prince</hi> very agreeable to the Natural <hi>Engliſh Genius;</hi> but he may eaſily be miſtaken by reaſon of the Corruptions of the laſt Reigns, which as they began at the Court, ſo have they moſt infected thoſe who moſt reſort thither. So that I know nothing of greater importance to him, than good information and due conſideration of the Natural <hi>Genius</hi> of the Body of this People, and how to diſtinguiſh that from the Degenerate Diſpoſitions of thoſe who have moſt acceſs to him.</p>
            <p>Their <hi>Natural Genius</hi> is Honeſt, Plain-dealing, yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderate and very Provident, (as manifeſtly appears in our Conſtitution of Government and Common Law, if rightly conſidered,) Induſtrious, Couragious, Conſtant, and Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; and, which I will mention as the great commendation of all, addicted to ſincere and ſubſtantial Religion; but ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horring Diſhoneſt, deſpiſing Tricks and Craft, and diſdain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Violence and Oppreſſion; and accordingly in matters of Religion, equally abhoring Hypocricy and Formality, and deſpiſing Superſtition. This might many ways be proved, but would require a particular Tract to do it as it ſhould be: And though it might ſeem otherwiſe to ſuch as converſe moſt with the moſt degenerate part of the Nation, yet even in them may be diſcerned the Natural Principles of theſe Diſpoſitions not totally extirpated, which makes them in many things more eaſie to be cured. And theſe Natural Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſitions are ſo agreeable to uncorrupted Reaſon and to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:66322:13"/>Genuine Primitive Chriſtianity, that it is not only Civil Prudence, but an indiſpenſible Duty to God to treat ſuch a People accordingly, and to endeavour not only the Reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution but Exaltation of this natural Temper, according to the moſt excellent Means of our moſt Holy and Admirable Religion, and no leſs imprudence and indiſcretion than Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety to do otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>But there are <hi>two Temptations,</hi> to which a Prince natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally Magnanimous and Prudent, may be obnoxious, which would certainly make his Government of ſuch a People ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry uneaſie, and therefore ought to be avoided with great Caution, and a pious and prudent Reſolution. The <hi>one</hi> is an <hi>Obſtinate Wilfulneſs,</hi> which often runs, and eſpecially by oppoſition, into a <hi>Gygantick Inſolence,</hi> without due regard to Reaſon, Juſtice, or Religion; that is, without due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard either to God or Man: Which is not true Magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity; for that is apt to exert it ſelf on all occaſions, in a generous and Free Submiſſion to Reaſon, Juſtice, and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, and rather to part with its own than uſurp upon another's Right: But the other is a mere Brutiſh Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, odious both to God and Man, as inconſiſtent with Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence as different from true Magnanimity, and ordinarily of moſt pernicious Conſequence; of which <hi>England</hi> in this laſt Age hath had very remarkable Examples. And for this purpoſe it is abſolutely neceſſary to beware of <hi>Flattarers and Paraſites,</hi> and abandon them, or keep them at a great diſtance when they are once perceived for ever after, as moſt dangerous and pernicious Perſons.</p>
            <p>The <hi>other</hi> is a <hi>Subtil Craft,</hi> which often impoſeth upon Men under the appearance of <hi>Prudence;</hi> but in truth is as far different from genuine Prudence, as it is inconſiſtent with true Generoſity of Mind: This likewiſe is very odious both to God and Man; and however it may prevail for ſometime, yet uſually proves of pernicious Conſequence at laſt; as by Experience in the laſt Race of our Kings is eaſily obſervable in theſe Nations. Nothing is more neceſſary to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:66322:13"/>a good Accord between a Prince and People, and for the Proſperity of both, than <hi>Mutual Confidence.</hi> And nothing doth more deſtroy or debilitate ſuch a mutual Confidence, than ſuch crafty Projects and Practices; which are the more carefully to be avoided by how much the more they have been practiſed here, and with ſuch unhappy Succeſs: And no leſs are the Inſtruments thereof to be avoided and abandoned.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Both</hi> theſe as they are carefully to be avoided by a truly Magnanimous and Prudent Prince, upon the General Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations aforeſaid, ſo are they much more upon this <hi>ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Conſideration</hi> of their <hi>Contrariety and Diſagreement with the natural</hi> Genious <hi>of this People.</hi> Such violent and unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Means can never produce any durable Effect of Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Happineſs; but ſooner or later will be diſappointed, and make the Memory of thoſe who uſe them odious and diſhonourable with all Poſterity.</p>
            <p>And beſides all this, there is <hi>a farther</hi> ſpecial Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of great moment, <hi>in relation to the Prince hmiſelf,</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their <hi>Inconſiſtence with his own Declaration,</hi> and the Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude (I will be bold to ſay it) which he oweth the People of theſe Nations (though I deny not in the leaſt his Merit) for the Honour they have done him. And upon this occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, I cannot but take notice of that late Emblem at the <hi>Hague,</hi> of a Balance with a Sword preponderating Three Crowns, and <hi>Praemia non aequant</hi> for a <hi>Motto,</hi> as a piece of mean pedantick Flattery, below the Gravity and Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of ſuch a State, and too light a Complement for real Worth and Merit.</p>
            <p>As it is our <hi>Happineſs</hi> to have a Prince ſo agreeable to our narural <hi>Genius,</hi> ſo its ſome <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nhappineſs</hi> to him to meet with ſo many among us ſo much degenerated from it. But then nothing can make him a more <hi>Glorious Inſtrument,</hi> than to reſtore us to our ancient Vertue; nor any thing give him greater Advantage for farther Honour. And this being ſo Fundamental a Matter, both for the Honour of the King,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:66322:14"/>and the Good and Happineſs of the Nation (beſides that it is a principal End of Government) no Man, who is well affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to either, can be offended, if I conſider it with that Freedom and Plainneſs, which a Matter of ſuch Importance doth deſerve; But if any be, I ſuppoſe he will think it too great an Evidence againſt himſelf that he is not ſuch, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcover it. This certainly is no more than neceſſary, ſince ſo ſubtil and powerful is the Venom of <hi>this Corruption,</hi> that there is danger otherwiſe leſt it ſhould invade even the Prince himſelf e'r he be aware, and hath already approach'd him with very evil Effects. It <hi>began</hi> apparently ſoon after the Deceaſe of Q. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> by her ſuppoſed wiſe, but in truth, weak Succeſſor, who being a timorous Perſon, and (as is natural to ſuch) addicted much to Craft (wherein he gloried, though it often failed him, and indeed fool'd him) attracted moſt of that Temper to him, and tainted others: And Prince <hi>Henry,</hi> who was of another Spirit, being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happily taken off by an untimely Death, this kind or Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers and Politicians moſt eaſily inſinuated themſelves into the naturaly diſpoſed Humour of his Succeſſor; who, had he been directed by Perſons of the right <hi>Engliſh Genius,</hi> might have been more happy. The ſame Spirit, though caſt out for a while, returned again, and with greater Force poſſeſs'd his next Succeſſor; and from thence hath this ſort of Policy greatly prevailed, but with ſuch Iſſue as the World hath ſeen. Nor is it yet extinct, but offers fair to re aſſume its former Place and Power: So that were not this King a Perſon of more Generoſity and Vertue, he would certainly be carried away with the Stream of our degenerate Politicks. But beſides thoſe Vertues natural to him, he hath had Three years <hi>Experience</hi> of notorious <hi>Diſappointments,</hi> to warn him of the Danger of their Counſels: Only having been ſo little reſident amongſt us, it cannot be expected he ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently be ſenſible of the ſecret Cauſes of his Diſappointments, or the pernicious Effects of their Counſels; and therefore no greater Service can be done him, and by Conſequence, to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:66322:14"/>the whole Kingdom, than by laying theſe things as plain and naked before him as poſſible; and to detect or ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently point out the principal Agents: For it concerns him little leſs to beware of this Generation and their Policies, than it did the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to avoid the <hi>Canaanites</hi> and their Manners.</p>
            <p>But firſt it may be fit to explain the <hi>Nature of this Dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neracy; and of the Humours by which it is fed</hi> and nouriſhed. Which are plainly a Compoſition of Atheiſm, Infidelity, Covetouſneſs and Ambition, with ſome other ſuch kind of Ingredients, which make up that Corrupt and Diabolical Humour called <hi>Self,</hi> the very Sperm and Spirit of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent. The Propenſions and Motions of all things in Nature, as hath been well obſerved by that great Philoſopher, Sir <hi>Fra. Bacon,</hi> are more ſtrong and vigorous to the <hi>Common Good,</hi> than to the Private Good of Self. And it is apparent that no Sect, Religion, or Philoſophy of Men, doth ſo much exalt the Common Good above the Private Good of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Men, as the Chriſtian: Whence, as that ſubtile ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervant Philoſopher doth well infer, it plainly appears that it was the ſame Author, who ſo wiſely and powerfully or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered and diſpoſed the Courſe of Nature, that inſtituted the Chriſtian Religion. The Primitive Chriſtians were confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable to the Integrity of their Inſtitution. The true <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Spirit, retaining much of the Integrity of Nature in that reſpect, and kindly receiving the Chriſtian Inſtitution with much Simplicity and Devotion, was accordingly very Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious and Reſolute to prefer the Good and Service of its Country before all private Reſpects. Nay, the very Heathens in all parts of the World have left Noble Examples of the ſame Generous Diſpoſition. But we have had a generation in this laſt Age ſprung up amongſt us, of ſuch degenerate greedy Souls, as make no ſcruple to expoſe the Rights and Liberties of their Country, and the Honour and Safety of their Princes for their own inſatiable Avarice and Ambition; and of ſuch degenerate narrow Souls as will ſee all run into
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:66322:15"/>Conſuſion before they will expoſe any thing of their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Intereſt to hazard to prevent it.</p>
            <p>The Principal Ingredient is ſome kind of <hi>Atheiſm and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelity,</hi> at leaſt an unnatural and <hi>bruitiſh Stupidity and Inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility</hi> of the moſt Excellent Being in the World, of the admirable Excellence of the Chriſtian Religion, and of the proper End of Man's Being and Buſineſs upon Earth. Theſe of this humour are a kind of <hi>Brutes,</hi> and little better, but like to end in much worſe. But beſides theſe there are a kind of <hi>Monſters,</hi> who Glory in their ſhame, <hi>cum ratione inſanire;</hi> and in truth are <hi>Inſani quod ad hoc,</hi> though in other matters rational and ingenious; which is a common caſe. Their Minds are corrupted, their Wills and Affections firſt by ſome unhappy accident perverted, and that is ſuch a Bias and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice upon the Judgment that no Reaſon can be offered, but the Invention ſhall immediately be excited and imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to return an Anſwer, and the Judgment thereby preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſtracted from all ſound and impartial Deliberation. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides many having ſinn'd themſelves into a State of Deſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and being once paſt hope of Benefit by Religion, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to convince them is to argue againſt their Intereſt (which may often be perceived by their Heat and Concern,) as is to no more purpoſe than to caſt Pearls before Swine. An Opinion it is unnatural, abſurd, and monſtrous; and as it well deſerves, will e'er long become infamous. In the mean time if any out of Piety and Charity have a deſire to relieve any ſuch unhappy Creature, his application muſt be to that part, which was firſt debauched, to the Will and Affections, by raiſing of Hope that the Caſe is not deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate; make him willing to hear Reaſon, and conſider it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partially; and to do but in this Caſe what a wiſe Man would do in any other of great Moment. But this by the by.</p>
            <p>When Men are once fallen into this Unhappineſs either through Infenſibility or Prejudice, that they ceaſe to proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the proper End of their Life and Being, they preſently ſet up ſome Idol inſtead thereof; and adoring and courting
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:66322:15"/>that with the Affections proper for a more Excellent End, they become exorbitant and infatiable. And hence pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed thoſe <hi>other Ingredients,</hi> of inſatiable <hi>Covetouſneſs</hi> and <hi>Ambition;</hi> while true Riches and true Honor are neither eſteemed nor underſtood, but empty and vain Shadows are purſued inſtead of the Subſtance by indirect and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Means. The proper Means of acquiring of Wealth, are honeſt Induſtry and Frugality: And the proper Means of acquiring Honor are Honeſty, Juſtice, and Generous Actions, for the Good and Benefit of other Men, and of ones Country. For real <hi>Honor</hi> is only the Approbation of a Mans Integrity, Virtue and Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous Actions, by God, Angels and Men. <hi>Titles</hi> are only Enſigns of this, which if it be wanting, they are a Lye and an Impoſture. Yet have they in this Age been conferred upon ſo many without either actual Merit or real Worth; that they are become in a great meaſure inſignificant: Nay, ſo frequently for baſe, diſhoneſt, and unworthy Services, that they are in danger of what hath happened to ſome Words, which though originally of a good Signification, have by Abuſe become in time to ſignifie the quite contrary.</p>
            <p>And for <hi>Riches,</hi> how little is the true Uſe thereof un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood by thoſe who uſe ſuch indirect Means to obtain them! They ſell their Country, their Prince, and their own Souls to Purchace them; and when they have them, either prodigally ſpend them upon Luxury and Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; or imploy them to corrupt themſelves with Pride and Vanity; or hoard them up to make Fools of their Poſterity. And while theſe things are ſo little under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, and yet ſo much admired, Virtue, and the true Excellence of Man is neither regarded nor underſtood. We complement inſignificant Titles, Fine Cloaths, and Foot-men: But ſhould any of the Ancient Sages, or even Chriſt himſelf, appear amongſt us in their own Apparel, they would certainly be deſpiſed, not only by the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:66322:16"/>Boes, and Fops of the Town, by our Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Courtiers, and Phariſaical Doctors, but by moſt of our well-bred Gentlemen, and many, who ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to others, and believe themſelves to be very reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious. They ſhould be kept at a diſtance, and taught better Manners than to call <hi>Herod</hi> a Fox, or a <hi>Scribe</hi> or a <hi>Phariſee</hi> an Hypocrite; nay, be reputed Mad, at leaſt be gravely cenſured as too hot and imprudent by ſuch as have little better Heat in their Heart than of a Dunghil, or Light in their Head than of an <hi>Ignis Fatuus.</hi> Nor can it be otherwiſe while Mens Eyes are dazeled with the Pomps and Vanities, and their Minds tinctured or infect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the falſe Wiſdom of the World.</p>
            <p>This is the true Nature of that Degeneracy which hath debaſed the Ancient Glory of this Kingdom, and of thoſe corrupt Humors by which it is fed and nouriſhed. <hi>Its Age and Growth</hi> is alſo eaſie to be proved; for which I will offer but one Conſideration. Let any one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare but the <hi>Knights</hi> of <hi>Queen Elizabeth</hi> with the <hi>Peers</hi> of her Succeſſors, and he may ſoon perceive what Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence there hath been of Prudence in the Princes, and of Vertue in their Subjects. Both ſhe and her Subjects better underſtood the Nature of <hi>True Honon,</hi> the Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between the <hi>Subſtance</hi> and the <hi>Titles,</hi> and the true Uſe of the latter. She had more Prudence than to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſe and vilifie thoſe Noble Enſigns by Prodigality or Abuſe: And they more Senſe of Vertue and Merit, which are the Eſſence of Honor, than to be fond of the Titles, well knowing that the Glory of Virtue is more Sincere and Illuſtrious without them, and that its Reward ſhould he more like it ſelf, Real and Subſtantial. Nor were <hi>Riches</hi> then ſo commonly covetted with ſuch inſatiable Greedineſs, nor proſecuted by ſuch indirect Means, nor abuſed ſo unworthily, or ſordidly hoarded up: but either very much neglected in reſpect of our Times, or imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Service of the Publick: in ſo much that Sir
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:66322:16"/>
               <hi>Francis Walſingham,</hi> the famous Secretary of State, who had few equals in Merit of Virtue, had no greater Title than of a Knight, died Poor, and left little or no Eſtate, but a moſt honorable Memory behind him. Our <hi>Nobility</hi> then were of the Old <hi>Engliſh</hi> Stock, and it was their Glory then as in ancient Times, with a generous Emulation to venture their Perſons, and employ their Eſtates for the Service of their King and Country. And our <hi>Commons</hi> then, and in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Times, thought it matter of Duty and Fidelity, as well as their Right, to take notice of the Miſcarriages even of our Kings themſelves, and to inform them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and aſſert the Rights of their Country againſt all Invaſions and Encroachments. The baſe diſhoneſt no leſs than diſhonorable Arts of packing of Parliaments, and corrupting the Publick Truſtees of the Nation, and falſe Pretences for cheating the People of their Money, were then unknown. But what was freely given, was as freely remitted if the Occaſion ceaſed. Nor was the Publick Revenue then waſted upon Paraſites and Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers, inſatiable Cormorants, or in exceſſive Salaries and Penſions to maintain Luxury and Impiety. Nor was the Trade then known of Purchaſing the Votes of the Rabble with Ale and Roaſt-Beef, and then expoſing them for Sale for Penſions, Offices, or other Gratuities. But the Publick Good, the Honor and Honorable Service of the Prince, and the Honor, Service, and Proſperity of their Country, was the common Study and Ambition of all, and the Favor and Bleſſing of God was with them.</p>
            <p>But <hi>her Succeſſors</hi> being Perſons of mean Spirit, forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king their Dependence upon the Supreme Governor of the World, and flying to and taking up with no leſs deceitful than diſhoneſt Tricks of Craft, inſtead of the more manly and more chriſtian Prudence of the moſt Generous and moſt Proſperous of their Predeceſſors, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted People of agreeable Diſpoſitions from all parts of the Nation; and fill'd the Court firſt, and at laſt our
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:66322:17"/>Parliaments too, with this baſe and degenerate Brood, no leſs pernicious to the Kings themſelves, than to the People and whole Kingdom: Whoſe <hi>Loyalty</hi> is only Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, and Tricks and Knavery their greateſt <hi>Policy;</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving little Senſe of Providence, and as little of true Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity, will ſell their Country to ſerve their Prince, and their Prince to ſerve themſelves: A generation more ambitious of empty Titles, than induſtrious in the direct ways of true Honor; and more ready to devour the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies of their Country raiſed for Publick Service, than to ſerve their Prince either with their Perſons or their Purſes after the rate of ancient Times; more concerned at a little Breach of their own Priviledge than at a groſs Violation of the Rights of their Country; and more apt to deſert the Honor or Service of the Prince for fear of a Potent Perſon, or to ſerve a Turn, than to encounter the diſpleaſure of either by any generous Act of Fidelity for the Service of their Country, or of their Prince himſelf.</p>
            <p>This is that Wicked <hi>Cananitiſh</hi> Generation, and theſe their corrupt Manners, which the King of neceſſity muſt firſt caſt out or ſubdue, if ever he will be a Glorious In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument in the Service of the God of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> His Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration was Juſt and Honorable, his Undertakings Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful and Glorious, and his Propoſals to the Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion reaſonable and worthy of himſelf, and of his Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings: But it was, as I ſaid, his Unhappineſs (and ours too) that he met at firſt with ſuch degenerate Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons before he well underſtood them: yet will it be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>his greater Honor to extricate himſelf and the Nation out of the Snares and Intanglements of their pernicious Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licies: To which the unhappy Examples of his immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Predeceſſors, and his own Experience are great and ſpecial Obligations, beſides the Obligations of his own Declaration and Undertakings; and ſuch as undoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly would make his neglect inexcuſable, and ſuch a Neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect his End unſucceſsful and inglorious. Never was the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:66322:17"/>Treaſure of the Nation more, or ſo much exhauſted in three Years time: Never had we greater Loſſes in our Trade, nor greater Loſſes of Men both at Land and Sea without Fighting; never braver Fleets, nor ever any ſo baffled and unſucceſsful: Never a braver Army than this laſt Campain, and a more Couragious and Induſtrious Prince to Lead them, and yet never leſs effected. And what can all this be imputed to, but the Diſpleaſure of Providence and Evil Counſels? I am for the uſe of Means as well as others: but they muſt be proper Means, and all neceſſary Means muſt be well uſed. Armies are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, and Fleets neceſſary, and Money neceſſary for all theſe: But if we think nothing elſe neceſſary, and will ſtill over-look other Neceſſaries, and greater Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, we connot rationally expect any better Succeſs this Year than we had the laſt: And of that what other Conſequence can we expect, but that the People of this Nation will grow weary of their Burden? and the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence of that expected, and poſſibly deſigned by ſome too far intruſted in Counſels or Affairs, that they ſhould alſo grow weary of their King. So much Miſchief al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſuſtained, and ſo great danger of more for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, doth certainly deſerve to be well conſidered, and that good enquiry be made into the Cauſes and proper Remedies thereof. Experience and the Judgment of all Wiſe Men in all Ages of the World, abundantly prove that it is in vain to expect any great matters from Force of Men and Armies in the Field, if the Counſels at home be either unfound or betrayed: For his Majeſties Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and Conduct in the Field, it is, for ought I can find, ſo far above all Exceptions, that it ſeems to be the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Difficulty that his Enemies have to encounter; ſo that the only things to be enquired of are whether there be not ſome Treachery, Unfaithfulneſs, or other great Fault in our Counſels and Managements at home? And whether there may not be ſomething which may have provoked
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:66322:18"/>the Diſpleaſure and Disfavor of the Divine Providence?</p>
            <p>And to begin at the Root of all, I may be bold to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm that the King hath been betrayed in the principal Point of all, that is, of his ſpecial Duty to God in his Place and Circumſtances, by ſome of his Clergy; and to offer it to any of them all to anſwer with a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and as in the Preſence of God my <hi>Queſtions Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logical</hi> in Relation to his Caſe, ſo as to clear that Point. If he hath not done for the Honor and Service of God what is Circumſtances and the Duty of his Place under the Obligation of a Solemn Oath do require, though it be principally through the Fault of another, how can he expect the Favor and Bleſſing of the Providence of God to be with him for his own Honor? And though I believe there are but few who are actually guilty of this Unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, yet muſt all, who at any time ſtand in the place of Watchmen, anſwer for his Blood, if he dye in his Sin, and they do not faithfully diſcharge their Duty by plain, and timely Warning in the Name of God, and with the Authority becoming the Miniſters of the Divine Majeſty. They hold the Place of Prophets, and the Duty of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets is incumbent upon them; and if they have not the Light and Diſcerning of Prophets, it is their own Fault, who encumber themſelves ſo much with the Pomps and Vanities, and the unneceſſary Superfluities of the World. If they know not in this their Day the things which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to their Duty and their Peace, but ſuffer this Prince alſo to miſcarry through Evil Counſels, which have been the Bain of ſo many of his Predeceſſors in this Nation, what can they expect but to be ſpewed out as unprofit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Servents? —<hi>to be thrown out with Scorn, that Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel Angels may our Church Adorn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I hope better things from ſuch as are now in Place.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:66322:18"/>
            <p>This unhappy Error in the Service of God hath, I doubt, expoſed him to the Miſchief of Unfaithfulneſs in ſuch as he hath imployed and intruſted in his Service, the Divine Providence permitting him to feel the Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences of ſuch Polices for Conviction of this Error. The <hi>Effects of our Management</hi> are viſible to the World; the <hi>Perſons</hi> imployed are likewiſe known; and <hi>the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agement it ſelf</hi> is much complained of; too much per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps when and as it ſhould not, and as much too little, if there be juſt Cauſe, when and as it ſhould. If the Management be ill, and the <hi>Perſons</hi> imployed unskilful and unable, the Fault is in the Choice principally, and the Remedy is to put them out and chooſe better; but if the Perſons be able, and the Management ill, the Fault then is in the Perſons imployed and intruſted; and they are not only to be turned out, but farther puniſhed as their Miſdemeanors deſerve, and the Damage requires: And if this be not done as it ought, the Fault reſts upon them who ought to do it, and yet neglect their Duty. And becauſe for Miſdemeanors of all great Officers, the <hi>Houſe of Commons</hi> are the general Inquiſitors for the whole Kingdom, if there be any ſuch ill Manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as is believed and talked on, it muſt be a great Fault of Unfaithfulneſs to God, to the King, and to the Kingdom, if they ſhould not impartially inquire into it, and faithfully uſe the moſt proper Parliamentary Means to have it effectually and ſpeedily redreſſed.</p>
            <p>And this is the Duty, not only of the whole Houſe, but of every <hi>particular Member</hi> of it. They are Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitors for the whole Kingdom, as the Grand-Jury of each County are for their reſpective Counties. And as every <hi>Grand Jury-man,</hi> who knows any thing Preſentable, and doth not Preſent it, doth violate his Oath and Duty to his Country, ſo doth every Member of Parliament, who knoweth any thing neceſſary to be conſidered there, and doth not honeſtly acquaint the Houſe with it, and earn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtly
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:66322:19"/>move to have it conſidered, no leſs violate his Truſt and Duty of Fidelity both to his King and Country. Was it certain that the whole Houſe would oppoſe him, an Honeſt and a Wiſe Man would notwithſtanding be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to diſcharge his Duty faithfully; nay, ſo much the more careful to do it to clear himſelf, that he might not be guilty, ſo much as by Silence, of any defect in Duty to his Prince or to his Country. And was this weighty Duty well conſidered as it deſerves, we ſhould have leſs Scuffling to get into the Houſe, and more honeſt and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Behaviour there than we too often have had. But that which for many Ages hath been the Root of Remedy, for all our Maladies, hath in this been ſo cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, that it hath moſt of all needed Remedy, and yet hath moſt obſtinately reſiſted it. But of all I have moſt admired at thoſe whom I took to be the beſt, Men of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety, Religion, Conſcience, Fidelity to their Prince, and Affection to their Country, to ſee ſuch frighted, nay even laughed and ſhamed out of all theſe. I wiſh ſuch may receive this Admonion, and better conſider their Duty in time, and do works meet for Repentance, that is, give Glory to God by ſo much greater Acts of Fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity by how much they have at any time failed therein: For otherwiſe they will be called to a ſtrict Account, wherein their little Prudentials will little avail them. And for this purpoſe to ſuch as deſire to diſcharge their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience well, I ſhall recommend the Account of the Good Steward in Sir <hi>Mat. Hale,</hi> as a good Pattern how to treat it.</p>
            <p>But in the mean time there is <hi>another Account,</hi> that ſuch Publick Truſtees are to be imminded of; and that is an Account of their Actions, if ill, or not faithful ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Truſt repoſed in them, which the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of <hi>England,</hi> who intruſt them, or any one of them may call any of them to. The meaneſt Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in <hi>England</hi> may maintain a Suit againſt the King
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:66322:19"/>himſelf, if he have juſt Cauſe, and the ordinary Judges ought to give Judgment for him and do him Right. He may likewiſe complain in Parliament, if he have Cauſe proper for that, of any Grievance by the King or his Miniſters, or of any Miſdemeanor by any Member or Members of Parliament, or if it be the Speaker himſelf. And what one may do, more may do, the Marriners may do it, the Merchants may do it, the Judges, Serje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants and other Lawyers may do it, the Lord Mayor, Aldermen and Common-Council of <hi>London</hi> and the other Cities may do it, the Counties may do it, and all may do it; there is no Limitation of the Numbers, but only of thoſe who preſent the Petition, and that only by a late Act of Parliament. It is an Ancient, and a Fundamental Right of the Commons of <hi>England,</hi> and whoever ſhould dare to ſpeak againſt it, as ſome baſe Abhorrors did ſome Years ſince, though it were in Parliament, ought to be queſtioned for it, as a Betrayer of the Rights of his Country. For though Freedom of Debate be a neceſſary Privilege of Parliament, yet are there certain Bounds to it that may not be tranſgreſſed. Nor is the Power of the Houſe of Commons, or of the whole Parliament, ſo boundleſs or unlimited as ſome may imagine.</p>
            <p>This, as it is an Ancient and a Fudamental Right, ſo is it a Right as needful to be underſtood and put in Practice now as ever. This, if any thing that I can ſee, under God, muſt ſave both King and Kingdom: For the Lords, I can ſay nothing to them. But for the Repreſentatives of the Commons, I find many of them ſo affraid of Great Men, if not otherwiſe corrupted, that they avoid the Motion of a Petition againſt their Speaker, or a Lord-Commiſſioner of the Great Seal, though for the Honor of the Royal Authority, and the Execution of the Laws, (the Care of which is their ſpecial Duty) nay for the Honor of their own Houſe, and ſeek Evaſions as from ſome dangerous Matter. So that I ſee not
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:66322:20"/>whence we can expect Effectual Remedy for the Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs and Dangers ſo much complained of, but next under God from the Virtue of their Majeſties and the Great Body of the People, (comprehending I hope the greateſt part of the Lords) who are generally intire for the preſent Settlement. We have lately had a good Choice of <hi>Biſhops,</hi> moſt of them as good as our Clergy doth afford; and before that, a good Choice of <hi>Judges,</hi> moſt of them as good as the Profeſſion of the Law doth afford: And we have likewiſe I hope, as good a Choice of <hi>Sheriffs</hi> as could be expected. And what now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains, as things ſtand at preſent, to perfect all, and make both King and Kingdom happy, but</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>On their Majeſties part,</hi> That they reſolvedly endeavour, firſt to ſecure the <hi>Favour and Bleſſing of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God</hi> by ſome generous Acts for his Service, in the Reformation of the great Corruption of the Manners of the People; and for that purpoſe ſtrictly charge both ſome of the beſt of theſe Biſhops to be Faithful to God, and to their Majeſties, and to the Nation, in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainting their Majeſties fully and plainly with their Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in that reſpect, and what Almighty God requires of them under their Circumſtances; and likewiſe the Judges, to inform them of their Duty, and what they may and ought to do in that reſpect by the Laws of the Land, and then act accordingly: And Secondly, to confirm and ſecure the <hi>Confidence of the People</hi> in them, for a Juſt, Prudent, and Honourable Government: Which is to be done by generous and conſtant acts of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> ſuch as may demonſtrate the Accompliſhment of the Ancient Prophecy in his Majeſty's Perſon, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t Sponſus Sponſae ſic Juſtitia aſſocietur ei;</hi> that he ſhould eſpouſe Juſtice as inſeperably and cordially as a Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom his Bride; and that in reſpect of the Common Rights of the People, and publick Juſtice againſt Potent Offenders, as the Private Rights of particular Perſons;
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:66322:20"/>for which purpoſe the Judges are to be Adviſed with: And by like Acts of true <hi>Prudence;</hi> as 1. By Intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting ſuch only as are reputed Faithful, and without que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion intire and hearty for the preſent Settlement, and of undoubted Ability for their Employment in <hi>the Navy,</hi> for which purpoſe the Merchants and Marriners and Experienced Maſters are fit to be adviſed with, rather than ſuch who have hitherto been very unhappy in their Recommendations; likewiſe in <hi>the Militia</hi> of the Kingdom, and in <hi>Lieutenancy</hi> in the City; but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in the <hi>Great Offices of Truſt,</hi> in which the great Diſappointments we have had without other Viſible Cauſe than Unfaithfulneſs of Perſons Employed, ſeem to require a Change, in point of Reputation as well as of common Prudence: I may add, and in the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of the Peace;</hi> and that ſpecial care be taken that they be principally men of Sobriety, Virtue and Religion: And 2. By a frugal and provident Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agement of the <hi>Publick Revenue</hi> and great Supplies of the Nation, retrenching all unneſſary Expences, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when ſo great are neceſſary, and reducing exceſſive Salaries to Moderation.</p>
            <p>And next <hi>on the part of the Commons.</hi> That ſome Principal men of unqueſtionable Affection to their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties and the Government, and of Spotleſs Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, make <hi>an honeſt Enquiry</hi> into the Behaviour of their Repreſentatives, and of others intruſted in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agement of Publick Affairs, and then in an open Legal way repreſent what they find amiſs, both to the King and Council, and to the Parliament or the Committee of Greivances, ſo as that all the Commons of <hi>England</hi> may take notice of it. Half the number of the Houſe of Commons of Honeſt, Able and Couragious Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of good Intereſt in their Country, might do great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Service, though out of the Parliament, to their Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties and the Kingdom by this means than is imagined.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:66322:21"/>
            <p>And this is not only Lawful, but the Duty of every Loyal and Faithful Subject to promote it what he can: And provided they take good Advice and keep within the compaſs of the Law, will be not only Safe, but highly Honourable. Princes muſt ſee with other Men's Eyes, and hear with other Men's Ears: If they be not well informed, or miſinformed, eſpecially in matters of great Concern, it is their Unhappineſs more than their Fault, unleſs they will not hear, and matter of Duty and Fidelity in any Subject, who knows it, to endeavour faithfully all he can that they be rightly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed: And whoever doth not this, doth not the part of a Loyal and Faithful Subject to his Prince, and of an Honeſt Man to his Country. The Honour of the King, is for the Honour of the Kingdom; and the true Service of the King, is the Service of the Kingdom, and both, if really ſuch, are for the Honour and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God: So that whoever willfully neglects this Duty, is guilty of Unfaithfulneſs not only to the King, but alſo to his Country, and to God himſelf, and muſt Anſwer for it not only to Men, but to God, who knows the Secrets of all Hearts, and is not to be impoſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with pretended Prudentials and ſuperficial Evaſions. Nor can it be Offenſive to any Honeſt Perſon, who means well, in either Houſe of Parliament: But thoſe who are really ſuch in either, will be ready to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and promote it: And I doubt not but the Bleſſing of God will be with them. Beſides, it is for the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, Safety and Strength of any Government, that mutual Confidence and good Agreement be maintained between all Parties, which cannot poſſibly be, unleſs Publick Grievances be duly redreſſed, and notorious Criminals duly Puniſhed, or at leaſt Convicted, and then Pardoned if there be good reaſon for it: And that ſuch who are Suſpected be fairly Tryed, and all reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Satisfaction given to ſuch as Complain. To de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:66322:21"/>this, is Imprudence and Childiſhneſs, and was the fatal Error of <hi>Rehoboam</hi> and of our laſt Race of Kings. But we hope, we have Princes now of more Prudence and Virtue.</p>
            <p>That any Man, who may be queſtioned for Treaſon or Felony, may likewiſe be queſtioned for matter of Misdemeanour; and that whoever may enquire or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of the former, may likewiſe enquire and complain of the latter, is I think, without doubt. But what I mentioned of an <hi>Enquiry into the Behaviour of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentatives of the Commons of England,</hi> may ſeem ſtrange at firſt to ſuch as have not well conſidered it; but if well conſidered, it will appear not only Lawful, but Neceſſary and Commendable. That the Corruption of the Manners of the People of <hi>England</hi> in general, hath been deſignedly and induſtriouſly promoted, is by ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving and conſidering Men believed upon very good grounds: And it is likewiſe believed upon as good, that no part of the Nation hath been more attempted than the Publick Truſtees, though the greateſt and moſt deteſtable Wickedneſs that could be practiſed, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably with a farther wicked Proſpect of begetting an <hi>Odium</hi> in the People againſt Parliaments. This in the late Reigns was ſo Notorious, that it would be a high piece of Impudence to deny it now, eſpecially ſince his Majeſty hath taken notice of it in his Declaration. And whether any Reformation of ſo foul an Abuſe, and of the Corruption then introduced among our Truſtees, hath ſince been made, is certainly an Enquiry not only fit, but neceſſary; eſpecially conſidering the notorious Practice ſtill uſed in <hi>Elections,</hi> and manifeſt by the many Petitions upon that occaſion; the late Oppoſition in this very Parliament to a Bill but for reſtraining falſe <hi>Returns,</hi> thrown out after a ſecond Reading; the many Complaints of Abuſes in the <hi>Management of the Publick Affairs</hi> every where out of the Houſe, and the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:66322:22"/>little notice taken thereof in the Houſe; the Prevalence of <hi>Parties,</hi> and ſuch <hi>Practices</hi> in the Houſe, that a <hi>Petition of no mean Publick concern,</hi> the Contents being known to moſt of the Members, was lately rejected, by a party of the Houſe, taking a ſpecial Advantage of the Abſence of many others, to the Abuſe of the Houſe, the denial of an undoubted Fundamental Right of the Commons of <hi>England,</hi> tending to the Subverſion, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and Diſreſpect to the Royal Authority: To ſay nothing of other Matters worthy of Conſideration.</p>
            <p>As this is greatly Neceſſary, ſo is it no leſs Lawful. The <hi>Law of Nature</hi> allows all Men to enquire into the Actions and Behaviour of their Truſtees: And of all Truſtees, ſuch are moſt to be ſuſpected and looked after, who being moſt Intruſted, do moſt oppoſe or decline any ſuch Enquiry. Nor does any Law of the Land make it Unlawful. Nay, the Laws and Conſtitution of our Government allow it, and are not deſtitute of various means for Redreſs, as the Caſe may require, for any Unfaithfulneſs or Breach of Truſt, whether by the whole Houſe, or ſome part, or Member thereof. In <hi>Matters Diſcretionary,</hi> if the <hi>whole Houſe,</hi> or <hi>Major part</hi> prevail to do any thing amiſs <hi>without any Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> but ſincerely, intending it for the beſt, they are to be Excuſed, and the Commons who did not Chuſe better, muſt be content to bear the Inconveniences of their own ill adviſed Choice, and take care to mend it another time. But even in ſuch Matters, if there be <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent Corruption</hi> in the leading Men of the Houſe, they ought to be queſtioned for it. And in <hi>Matters of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Right</hi> of the Commons, <hi>or Duty</hi> of the Members, if they act contrary thereunto, though no other Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption be proved in particular, that is a manifeſt Breach of Truſt, for which the Leading Men at leaſt are to be queſtioned. In like manner any <hi>particular Member,</hi> if he do any thing amiſs through Corruption, or oppoſe, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpectfully
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:66322:22"/>ſlight, or contemn any undoubted Right of the Commons, or refuſe or willfully neglect any certain Duty incumbent upon him as a Member, and more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if either, with any diſreſpect to the King or Queens Majeſty, he ought to be queſtioned for it. And as to this matter of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfaithfulneſs by Neglect,</hi> whatever Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber hath any knowledge of any matter of Moment proper to be complain'd of, or moved in the Houſe, and either for fear of Reproach, or of the Diſpleaſure of any great Man, or that it will be rejected, or for any private reſpect to himſelf, or his Friends, doth not what in him lieth, that it may be complain'd of or moved in the moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and likely manner to take effect, is by his Conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or Silence, guilty of breach of Truſt, and therein a Betrayer of his Country: Whereas by the faithful diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of his Duty he might either ſucceed at firſt, or however give occaſion to detect divers evil Members, and to have them queſtioned, and at laſt perform his Truſt with greater Advantage. Nor is this ſo ſmall a matter as moſt imagine. For all the Unhappineſs of the Nation is plainly reducible to this, and muſt lye upon the Account of the Men profeſſing Sobriety, Religion and Concern for their Country, who by this Unfaithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs betray all. They firſt fail in their Fidelity to God through Fear of Men, and then by a juſt Judgment are given up to betray their King, Country, and their own Concerns by a baſe Fear, whatever pretences they make to cover it, where in truth no Fear is, that is, no juſt cauſe of Fear.</p>
            <p>Now for <hi>Redreſs</hi> in ſuch Caſes, if the Queſtion be concerning <hi>the Miſdemeanour of one or two, or a ſmall Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> of the Members, there is no queſtion but this may be redreſſed by the Major part in the Houſe, who, though all the reſt were culpable, yet may, if they pleaſe, only make Examples of the Principal; and it may be done upon Motion of any Member in the Houſe, or upon Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:66322:23"/>of any Commoner out of the Houſe, if there be Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to prove the Complaint; and eſpecially if the Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demeanor be committed out of the Houſe.</p>
            <p>But the greateſt Difficulty is in caſe of <hi>Corruption, and notorious <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfaithfulneſs and Breach of Truſt by the greateſt or prevailing part</hi> of the Houſe; which no Man, who hath obſerved the Occurrences of our Time, can think impoſſible. And as to this we have <hi>Precedents</hi> of whole Parliaments and their Acts reverſed by ſucceeding Parliaments: But ſuppoſe we have neither Act nor Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent in an extraordinary caſe, are we therefore with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Remedy? Have Lawyers no other Topicts to prove Law from? No Man, who hath read and conſidered the <hi>Doctor and Student,</hi> or <hi>Littleton,</hi> can think ſo. And in ſuch a Caſe as this, if the Laws and Conſtitution of our Government be well conſidered, why may not any great Body of the Commons, as the Lord-Mayor, Aldermen, and Common Council of <hi>London,</hi> or a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable number of Gentlemen of clear Reputation and good Intereſt, petition the King, and ſetting out firſt the Right, then the Violation and Breach of Truſt, and by whom, expreſſing and charging the principal Leaders, pray that that Parliament may be diſſolved, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſummoned to enquire concerning that Matter? I ſee not what can be ſaid againſt this with any colour, but for what I ſee ſubſtantial Matter to anſwer it. Let us look well into our Laws and Conſtitution, and we ſhall not find them ſo Defective as ſome through Ignorance have thought them, and therefore to ſupply Imaginary Defects, have ſometimes introduced very defective Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies, and neglected better.</p>
            <p>As for the other <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfaithfulneſs</hi> and breach of Truſt, which is committed, not by Acting or Speaking, but <hi>by Neglect and Silence:</hi> If any Member hath any <hi>ſpecial knowledge</hi> of any matter of Moment proper and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to be complained of in the Houſe, and doth not
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:66322:23"/>his Duty therein, that is ſuch a <hi>Concealment</hi> as makes him <hi>particeps criminis,</hi> and he may be queſtioned for it, as for any other Miſdemeanor by fact: But if he hath no other knowledge but what is <hi>common</hi> to the reſt or moſt of the Members, and doth not his Duty, whether the reſt do or not, he cannot be queſtioned for it in the Houſe, in particular: yet they who choſe him ought to take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of it, and mend their Choice another time: for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they wrong not only themſelves, but the King and Kingdom, in ſending an unfaithful or unfit Man, who is not able or not willing to do his part in ſo weighty a Buſineſs of Publick Concern; and beſides, he is guilty of Unfaithfulneſs before God, to whom he muſt account for his Actions toward Men.</p>
            <p>And of this Unfaithfulneſs I doubt there are but few, who can acquit themſelves before God, or Men either, while ſo many things are ſo much complain'd of elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, and even by Members themſelves, and yet ſo little thereof is examined or complain'd of in the Houſe. I will mention but two Inſtances of it in particular; in which whoever can clear himſelf to have honeſtly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged his Duty, may with the more Confidence and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Conſcience queſtion me for what I write, if he ſee Cauſe, and I ſhall as confidently ſubmit to his Sentence.</p>
            <p>The firſt I have mentioned before, <hi>a great Miſdemean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> of two Magiſtrates, Great Officers, and Members of the Houſe, contrary to the Duty of Magiſtrates, to a ſpecial Duty of the Houſe, to a known expreſs Command of her Majeſty, and that in diſcharge of her Duty by the Laws both of God and of the Land; and this done not in the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of his Majeſty beyond Sea, but as it were in his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and the Parliament ſitting; and ſo notorious, that it was done in the preſence of many other conſiderable Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and no leſs than Seven Reverend Prelates, who came on purpoſe to hear the Cauſe, being of great Conſequence, and concerning the moſt neceſſary Reformation of the abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:66322:24"/>Corruption of the Manners of the People. And t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h being ſo, who could acquit himſelf of Unfaithfulneſs, by his Silence and Neglect of ſuch a Cauſe as this, if no Man out of the Houſe had taken notice of it? But that a Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for ſuch a Cauſe as this, after Copies thereof deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to many of the Members, and the Contents thereof known to moſt, being offered to the Houſe, and put to the Vote, to be received or not, it ſhould be carried in the Negative, how can this be anſwered to God, to their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties, and to the Commons of <hi>England?</hi> and what can ſuch Members, as believe a Divine Providence, and have deſerted their Duty in ſuch a Caſe, expect but ſome ſevere Judgment upon themſelves and the Nation, if ſome effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Courſe, proportionable to the Offence, be not taken in time to prevent it?</p>
            <p>The other is this, That <hi>Management</hi> alone, though incertain whether through <hi>Corruption, Inability</hi> or <hi>Neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence,</hi> and <hi>reaſonable Suſpition,</hi> being proper and ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>Cauſes of Complaint againſt Perſons employed in great Offices of Truſt,</hi> (wherein the Publick Service is principally to be regarded, not the Honour or private Advantage of any particular Perſon) our Affairs have been ſo unhappily managed for three Years together; and yet there have been no more Complaints in the Houſe, or care taken to have Matters of ſo great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern for the Honour of the Government, and Benefit, or even Safety of the Nation enquired into. Is nothing to be regarded but Mony? Is it not of much great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Concernment, and even for the ſaving of our Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny at laſt, to have Perſons employed in other Places beſides the Treaſury, who are unqueſtionably Faithful, Able and Active? And what can this Neglect be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to but a ſtrange degenerate Fear of Men, whatever Prudentials are pretended, notwithſtanding the advantage of the Laws, and a good Cauſe to ſupport and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage the faithful diſcharge of Duty.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:66322:24"/>
            <p>Indeed, ſo epidemical is this Diſeaſe now become a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong our Gentry, that the Honeſt Performance of Duty, of Fidelity to God, to one's King and Country, ſeems to many no other than Heat, Indiſcretion, and Madneſs, as to me that Motto <hi>Peſtis Patriae Pigrities,</hi> ſeems never to have been more plainly verified then now in this Nation. And when I conſider the <hi>Cauſes</hi> of it, reflecting upon the groſs and impudent Impiety, Prophaneneſs, and Debauchery of the one part, and the want of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Courage and true Magnanimity in the reſt, to check it, either in Common Converſation, or by Authority in Parliament, I cannot but think it <hi>a Special Judgment of God upon the whole Nation,</hi> That they ſhould be deprived of Courage in things neceſſary for themſelves, who have ſhewed ſo little for the Honor and Service of God, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Advantage of the Laws to back them in the one Caſe as well as in the other. Nor do I believe that either Prince or People can proſper until their Radical Fault be amended; but rather that vile Abuſe even in, and to the Parliament it ſelf, will certainly produce ſome ſevere Judgment upon both, if connived at and ſuffered to paſs without due Correction.</p>
            <p>If Perſons Unfaithful and of Skill be imployed with Perſons of undoubted Fidelity but Unskilful, this gives a notable Advantage to the one ſort to betray all with the more Security under the cover of the others. And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this be not ſo in ſome Places of great Truſt and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I leave to them to enquire, to whom it moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly belongs, having mentioned ſomething to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe elſewhere. I ſhall therefore only take notice of ſome Perſons of undoubted Fidelity and Ability; who ſeem to be purpoſely kept out. Some Noblemen thus qualified we ſee are out, while others not equally qualified in both reſpects are imployed. But that I alſo leave to the Conſideration of others.</p>
            <p>Captain <hi>Dorrel,</hi> is a Perſon well known to be thus qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified;
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:66322:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> he gave very eminent Demonſtrations of it in that Engagement with the <hi>French,</hi> wherein few did the like: yet found he no better Reward or Encouragement than to be offered a Third Rate Ship the laſt Summer inſtead of a Firſt Rate, which he commanded before; and being thus put off, hath engag'd in a Voyage to the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> to the no leſt Diſhonor of our Management, than Diſſervice to Their Majeſties and the Nation.</p>
            <p>Captain <hi>Breholt</hi> had ſo ſign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>'d his Courage and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct in two Engagements, the one with an <hi>Algerine,</hi> and the other with a <hi>Dutch</hi> Man of War, which I have ſeen certify <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the hands of three Members of Parliament, and are, though imperfectly, mention'd in the <hi>Gazets,</hi> that K. <hi>Charles</hi> II. gave him a Gold Chain and Medal for it: and tho, he offer'd his Service by Petition to this King, which was referr'd to the Admiralty, yet could he obtain no An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, for above a Twelve Month after, and then was told there was no Vacancy; and at laſt was ask'd if he would accept of a Fireſhip.</p>
            <p>But it would be too long to name all the Worthy Perſons, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> even offered their Service in the Fleet, beſides more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ready to accept it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> generous withſtanding the Arbitrary Practices of the late Reigns, it is believed ſaved the Lives of ſome of the Lords; to the great hazard of his own, and almoſt ruine of his Family and Eſtate; yet can be not obtain any ſuitable Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſo much as in the other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Weſt Indies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laurance Braddon,</hi> for his generous undertaking to deteſt a moſt barbarous Murder, as it is believ'd, ſuffered Impriſonment during the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ate Reigns, and is ſuffer'd to want Neceſſaries in this, and can get no Imployment.</p>
            <p>And to conclude, ſuch is the Condition of Mr. <hi>Richad Bevat,</hi> who had taken great pains to detect the Unfaithfulneſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ne who is now in Cuſtody, for other Acts of Unfaithfulneſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>; and to detect <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> dangerous Practices here, and the like now at <hi>Jerſey.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Pity moved me to mention now; to whom many others might he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>led, no mean Inſtances of what ſort of Perſons are moſt kept or caſt out of Employment.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
